THIS EPISODE HAS SELF-HARM.
FOR HELP,
WWW.WANNATALKABOUTIT.COM.
MAGISTRATE
What gives you the right?
What gives you the right?!
Pleasure, sir. I'm Apolinar Moscote…
and I was named magistrate of this town.
No pieces of paper rules over our people.
And by the way,
we don't need any magistrate,
because there's nothing here to fix!
I should warn you, I am armed.
I would rather carry you alive
than carry your death
with me for the rest of my life.
ONE HUNDRED YEARS OF SOLITUDE
When Úrsula arranged
for the expansion of the house,
she had a special room built
for Melquiades
where he would spend hours on end
scribbling his enigmatic literature.
Arcadio…
Years later,
Arcadio would remember trembling
as Melquiades made him listen
to pages of his impenetrable writing.
Writings which,
although he couldn't understand,
were actually predicting his death.
QUIET STREET
The image of Remedios
ached somewhere inside Aureliano's body.
It was a physical sensation
that almost made it difficult
for him to walk,
like a pebble in his shoe.
Move!
Look, we already tried to be polite.
He's gonna have to learn the hard way.
My friend, you know
I'm at your complete disposal.
My boy and I will always stand by you.
We all stand with you.
Yes, I know.
He brought company.
We know he brought
some armed soldiers with him.
He also brought his wife and daughters.
Moscote!
Show your face out here now!
What is it, Buendía?
Listen closely.
Nearly 30 years ago,
these men and I started building Macondo.
We created roads, marked every street,
even built every house,
all of which was done
without the government.
And we want things to stay that way.
But you're welcome to live with us
if that's what you really want.
And not because you have
a bunch of gunmen here protecting you,
but out of courtesy and consideration
for your missus and daughters.
However, there are two conditions.
Everyone can paint their house
the way they see fit,
and your little soldiers
are leaving today.
And who will be enforcing law and order?
Well, us.
Can you believe Macondo's so peaceful
that its first person
has not even died from natural causes?
Much less unnatural.
We don't even have a cemetery.
Your word of honor?
Word of your enemy.
Because you and I are still enemies.
FOUNDED IN 1880
Amparo, grab an onion.
Yes, ma'am.
That one is rotten.
Mrs. Moscote…
I am Úrsula Iguarán de Buendía.
I see your husband mentioned mine.
They may have got off on the wrong foot,
but there's no purpose in you and I
doing the same as far as I'm concerned.
Mrs. Úrsula, I've heard your house is
the most exquisite of them all.
Well, my doors
are always open to your family.
Come visit us anytime.
-Thank you.
-Mm-hmm.
Wonderful to meet you, Mrs. Úrsula.
Likewise, Mrs. Moscote.
-That's all right.
-I'll pay.
-No need, ma'am. My gift.
-Thanks.
If he sees me using the daguerreotype,
then I won't hear the end of it.
All right. So you tell him
that since he's forgotten it exists,
I gave it to you.
I have achieved immortality.
THE CHOLERA
"You have to succumb
to the sophisticated talk
of the most inept in a secretarial class
in addition to…"
-Please come in.
-Thank you for having us.
We've brought you a gift.
Well, thank you.
-Made by my daughters.
-Ah!
You should see the tablecloths.
They're divine.
I can imagine. Visitación!
Could you please bring
shortbread and biscuits to the ladies?
Who is it?
Mrs. Moscote and her daughters.
-This is the living room.
-It's beautiful.
Mm. We have put
a lot of work into the house.
-I'm sure.
-Hmm.
-It can be quite a lot to maintain.
-Yes.
These are my daughters,
Amaranta and Rebeca.
-Pleasure.
-Nice to meet you.
Let's show Mrs. Leonor
and her daughters around.
-Welcome.
-This way.
Thank you.
Hey, a pianola!
Yeah, but it's out of tune.
Are you coming?
You really do have
a beautiful home.
Thank you so much.
-This is the Corridor of Begonias.
-Mm.
The girls' rooms are over there.
And that's the kitchen.
Please enjoy.
Thank you.
Our granary is over there.
How pretty.
Did you make this?
-And here…
-Do you like it?
And that's José Arcadio's laboratory.
Here.
You can have it.
Remedios, get out of there.
Thanks.
That afternoon,
Aureliano lost the hidden patience
that had made him wait
for a chance to see her.
And the house suddenly filled with love.
My darling Rebeca,
I think about you.
I dream about you.
Remedios in the soporific air
of 2:00 in the afternoon.
Remedios in the soft breathing of roses.
My beloved Pietro,
the days feel different now.
I cannot wait to be back in Macondo.
Remedios, everywhere.
Remedios, forever for me.
Remedios… everywhere.
It has been days
since your last letter.
Will I see you again?
Amparo!
The postman hasn't come.
♪ Oye, morenita, ven, dame tu amor… ♪
Hey! The world is spinning!
♪ De mi corazón ♪
♪ Oye, morenita, no quiero perderte ♪
♪ Y si tú me dejas, prefiero la muerte… ♪
Aureliano, tell us.
Who is the woman that's got you like this?
Like this how?
Like screwed.
Aureliano! It's eleven o'clock almost!
Aureliano then lost his memory,
just like during the times of oblivion.
And he recovered it on a strange dawn
in a room completely unfamiliar to him.
He didn't know how he had gotten there,
but he knew what his purpose was…
because he had carried it
hidden since childhood
in an impenetrable pocket in his heart.
Who is it?
You have to get it off your chest.
All of this anguish is killing you,
and I'm dying to know.
Remedios Moscote.
Well, first, you're gonna
have to convince your father.
And after that, her father.
Beneath her mockery,
Aureliano found a haven of understanding.
That dawn, he not only let go
of his doubts about his virility,
but also, the bitter weight
he had carried in his heart
for so many months.
What happened?
Your sister's eating dirt again.
"My darling…"
"I love you"?
I love you too.
Hmm.
What is this?
How did all these letters get here?
Here's the water.
What are you doing?
They're from the Italian.
"My beloved Rebeca,
I don't know when I come or when I go,
nor if all this is real or just a dream."
"Every decision I make contradicts
the decision that I made before it."
"And through all the things
that my soul conceives,
I have decided to go to Macondo
to ask for your hand in marriage."
"For your hand."
"I will let you know
the date of my arrival
in the next letter."
Amaranta also suffered
from the thorn of a lonely love.
Amaranta, open up.
She would lock herself
in the bathroom,
to find release
from the torment of a hopeless passion.
Everything all right?
Amaranta, open the door.
So he was also writing to Amaranta?
No.
She wrote him letters
and never sent them.
I wish I had never thought
about buying that pianola.
One more.
Another one.
That's how many?
More than ten.
There he is.
Moscote!
Buendía.
I thought we made a deal.
I've honored it.
I thought we both agreed no one
would have to paint their house blue.
No, sir.
You were very clear about it.
"Everyone can paint their house
the way they see fit."
That's what they're doing.
You're telling me
you have nothing to do with this?
The government gives away the paint.
I deliver it.
I don't force anybody.
Good day, gentlemen.
How unlucky can you get?
What is it?
Moscote.
He thinks he can just mock us.
Oh no. What's wrong?
What happened? What is it?
I've fallen in love.
Are you also in love with Crespi?
No, of course not.
Uh, Remedios Moscote.
You fell in love with
the daughter of my enemy, son?
Love is an awful plague.
Come here.
Come.
Does she love you back, son?
Well, I don't know.
I haven't said anything to her yet.
Well, then, forget about this little whim.
Move on, son.
It's not just a whim.
I really am in love with her,
and I'd like to marry her.
The Moscotes are
fine young women, José Arcadio.
Your problem is her father, not the girl.
Apolinar Moscote
will never be a part of this family.
Our family exists
because you and Mother had
the courage to confront your own parents.
Don't even think of comparing
your grandparents'
ridiculous superstitions
to the menace Apolinar Moscote is
to Macondo, for God's sake!
I'll ask for Remedios's hand in marriage…
with or without your blessing, Father.
José Arcadio Buendía…
you've lost one son.
Are you willing to lose another?
If we're marrying Aureliano off
to the daughter of Moscote,
then we will let
Rebeca marry Pietro Crespi.
Rebeca regained her health
as soon as she heard
about the arrangement.
And she wrote her fiancé a joyful letter
that she gave to her parents
for their approval.
Amaranta pretended to accept the decision.
So, Aureliano, which of my daughters
did you want to wed?
W… w… well, Remedios.
Do you mean Amparo?
No, sir.
Remedios.
Dolores, please bring
your sister Remedios.
Is something wrong?
I have six daughters old enough to marry,
and your son, specifically, likes
the one who still plays with dolls.
Mm.
What happened?
Get out of here.
All of you.
Now.
Let me handle it.
Mrs. Buendía,
could I have a moment with you… alone?
We had absolutely no idea.
-We would love to unite our two families.
-Yes.
-But Remedios is still a child.
-Well, that's pretty evident, isn't it?
And trust me, if we knew
which daughter he was referring to,
we wouldn't be here.
We will let Remedios marry Aureliano,
but… we will wait
until she's of conceiving age.
Under one condition.
What?
They get married in a church,
or there's no wedding.
Macondo has always been a secular town.
I will not accept their union
if it isn't first blessed by the Lord.
If you want is
for us to marry in the church,
that's fine by me.
Melquiades,
I need your advice.
Turns out that idiot of a magistrate,
he intends to bring the church to Macondo.
When have we ever needed a priest?
Right?
Melquiades?
Gypsy?
He's been like this for days.
Since when?
Since he finished his book.
When I die…
burn mercury for three days.
What do you mean, my friend?
Take him to the river tomorrow
and let him bathe.
The water will do him good.
Melquiades?
Melquiades!
I will never forgive your negligence.
Hurry! Come on! Over here!
Help me take him to the laboratory.
What are you waiting for?!
Let's go! Come on!
Mr. Buendía,
as the civil authority of our town,
it is my duty to inform you
that a drowned man's unearthed cadaver
presents a major threat to public health.
Melquiades is not a dead man.
He's immortal.
He himself revealed
the formula of his resurrection.
One, two, three.
Arcadio, the furnace.
Mercury!
Time has stopped,
and eternity has begun.
José Arcadio…
José Arcadio, stop.
Please.
I think that it's time
for you to put him to rest now.
Time has stopped,
and eternity has begun.
We come from water.
Time has stopped and eternity has begun.
Time has stopped,
and eternity has begun, Melquiades.
Arcadio never knew
that the woman who held him tightly,
embracing his loneliness and sorrow,
was really his mother.
-Rebeca.
-Pietro.
This gift is for you.
One, two, three.
Hmm.
The ballerina.
Do you like it?
Please.
She's angry.
Wait here.
Miss Amaranta.
What?
I hope you've been well.
I wanted to tell you I'll be opening
a store of musical instruments
with my brother… my brother Bruno.
So?
I could introduce him to you.
I swear you'll never marry my sister,
even if you have to walk over
my dead body on your way out.
Amaranta threatened Pietro
with killing herself.
I think it's best
if we get her out of town for a bit.
Perhaps meeting new people
will help heal her disappointment.
But I'm worried about you.
I don't want to leave you alone right now.
Don't worry about me.
I'll be fine.
The priority here is to avoid tragedy.
Hmm.
We'll be fine.
Okay.
Don't get your hopes up, sis.
Even if I have to kill you,
I will stop this marriage.
Be careful.
Death.
The card of Death?
The cards are never
to be interpreted literally.
So what does it mean?
Will I be happy?
Yes, you will,
but getting there
will not be easy for you.
It'll turn you upside down
like a giant whirlwind.
No, Rebeca.
Rebeca, we mustn't. No.
Rebeca, we're in your house.
No, Rebeca, please.
Rebeca, my dear.
Father.
Good afternoon, Mr. Buendía.
Have you seen Melquiades?
Have you seen Pietro's present?
Hmm?
The rich and wondrous
mechanical animals Pietro Crespi brought
dissipated José Arcadio Buendía's
affliction over the death of Melquíades,
transporting him
to his old days as an alchemist.
Some sort of map…
Aureliano, in turn,
had neglected the workshop
to teach young Remedios.
In my family,
I am the only person of legal age.
Although, my eldest son
will turn 21 in April.
They are all yours?
Well, absolutely. They're all legitimate.
Political affiliation?
José Arcadio Buendía
managed to connect
the wind-up ballerina
to the mechanism of the clock,
And the toy danced uninterruptedly
to the rhythm of its own music
for three days.
Three days.
It's been working for three days.
Do you know what that means, son?
That discovery excited him
more than any of
his other madcap endeavors.
Without Ursula's supervision,
he became lost in his own imagination.
Her skin became
coarse like bark.
Her hair turned to leaves.
Poor Apollo.
Apollo ultimately understood
that she'd never love him back
and that she'd never be his wife,
but then he made her this promise.
That from that moment on,
she would be his tree.
Listen, Moscote.
We have
no political affiliations here in Macondo.
I don't see the need for a census.
We all know each other here.
These are government orders.
José Arcadio?
Listen, that in-law of yours
is pushing it too far around here.
And I'm sorry, but the fact that one
of his daughters is marrying your son
doesn't give him the right
to do whatever he wants.
I think you should put a stop to this.
What's today?
Tuesday. Why?
I was thinking it might be.
But it's actually still Monday.
Úrsula's absence made
the house seem enormous and empty.
Prudencio.
Prudencio Aguilar.
How did you end up so far away?
The need for company led me to find you.
My dear, sweet, old enemy.
I was wondering where you were.
Macondo was
an unknown town to the dead
until its first dead man arrived.
Melquiades.
He showed us a little black dot…
on the maps of death.
Papa…
Mama…
Excuse me, Mr. Buendía.
-Is everything okay?
-Papa…
Prudencio…
Melquiades…
They are all so lonely in death.
What's today?
-Thursday.
-Hmm.
It still is Monday.
The time traveling machine
has broken down,
and Úrsula and Amaranta are so far away.
Ya! Ah!
Ah!
Stop!
Time has stopped,
and eternity has begun!
Ugh! Help!
-But man wasn't born…
-Help!
Stop!
-Ah!
-Oh!
-We were born to die!
-Ah! What's going on?
Call the neighbors!
-Help! Somebody help!
-To become…
To become… organic matter!
Mr. Buendía!
Stay calm--
No more!
You'll be all right. Easy. Easy.
Easy. It's all right. It's all right.
Easy. Easy. Easy.
It's all right. Calm down.
We were born to die.
To become…
And eternity has begun.
But man was not born to be eternal.
We were born to die.
To become organic matter.
To become memories
and oblivion in the hearts of men.
BASED ON THE NOVEL
BY GABRIEL GARCÍA MÁRQUEZ